Lieber mss., 1691-1945 LMC 1656
Lilly Library
Lieber mss.
1691-1945
1944
1945
1955
1956
2004
Lilly Library
LMC 1656
4 folios oversize
13 Boxes 6 standard, 7 custom
39 bound
The Lieber mss., 1691-1945, are papers of Richard Lieber, 1869-1944, director of the Indiana State Department of Conservation from its creation in 1919 to 1933.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Richard Lieber was born in St. Johann-Saarbrucken, Germany, on September 5, 1869, the son of Otto and Maria Henriette Julie (Richter) Lieber. He attended Municipal and Royal Lyceum in Dusseldorf, Germany, and then studied English speech and literature in England in 1890. In 1891, he came to United States, where he worked in a hardware store in Indianapolis, Indiana. On August 28, 1893, Lieber married Emma Rappaport, 1874-1955. He engaged in various businesses in Indianapolis. He was a music and art critic for the Indianapolis Journal and Indiana Tribune for about eight years. In 1915, he became chairman of the Indiana State Park Committee. He was appointed military secretary with the rank of Colonel by Governor Goodrich in 1917, and appointed Secretary of the Indiana Board of Forestry in 1917. Lieber was appointed as the first director of Indiana State Department of Conservation in 1919, a position he held until his resignation in 1933. He died on April 15, 1944.
Scope and Content Note
Included in the collection are 1) 39 diaries of Lieber, 1890, 1891, 1895, 1909-1944, which include scrapbook material, i.e. newspaper clippings, programs, pictures, tickets, some letters, etc., as well as diary entries. Loose scrapbook material in volumes which have been rebound has been removed and placed in folders labeled by years in a manuscript box labeled: "Scrapbook Material from Diaries 1909-1942." 2) Speeches and writings of Lieber, 1893-1944, mainly 1930-1944, chiefly on state parks and conservation. 3) The booklet Indiana at A Century of Progress. International Exposition Chicago 1933, regarding the murals produced by Thomas Hart Benton. 4) Lieber family letters and papers in German, 1691-1899. 5) Protokoll Buch der Freisinnigen Sonntagsschule, Indianapolis, Ind., 1896-1905. 6) Letters to Richard Lieber from prominent men in the United States, 1916-1937. 7) Correspondence, 1943-1944, of Lieber on stream pollution, the Indianapolis post-war planning board, etc. 8) Resolutions of various organizations on the death of Richard Lieber, 1944. 9) Loose-leaf notebook of "Plans of a Department of Conservation, State of Indiana," 1908-1919. 10) Miscellaneous typewritten, mimeographed, printed and pictorial material on national and state parks. 11) Photograph albums and unmounted photographs of Richard Lieber, members of his family, Lieber family homes, parks and historic sites in Indiana and other parts of the United States, etc. 12) Newspaper clippings, 1905-1950, relating to Richard Lieber. 13) photostats of some 1913 and 1914 numbers of the Preussische Gesetzsammlung.
Additions to the collection include: a receipt for the use of property later known as Turkey Run State Park, Sept. 28, 1881; Lieber's military commission as Colonel and military secretary, May 11, 1917; certificate of recognition from Chicago Regional Planning Association, 1937; and photocopy of honorary doctorate from Wabash College, June 7, 1942.
Correspondents represented in the collection include: Lyman Abbott, George Ade, Claude Gernade Bowers, Calvin Coolidge, Stanley Coulter, George Creel, Frederic Adrian Delano, James Putnam Goodrich, Herbert Hoover, Charles Evans Hughes, Cordell Hull, Frank Billings Kellogg, Franklin Knight Lane, Louis Leon Ludlow, Thomas Riley Marshall, Harry Stewart New, Samuel Moffett Ralston, James Whitcomb Riley, Theodore Roosevelt, Ellery Sedgwick, Ordway Tead, Frederick Van Nuys, Woodrow Wilson, and Raymond Eugene Willis.
For biographical information see Emma (Rappaport) Lieber, Richard Lieber. Indianapolis, 1947. (Lilly F531 .L68 L4)
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1944, 1945, 1955, 1956, 2004
Indiana--Politics and government; Lieber, Richard, 1869-1944
- 1691-1941, Apr. (Box 1)
- 1941, May-1945 (Box 2)
- Photographs (Box 2)
- Speeches (Box 2)
- Printed (Box 3)
- Photographs (Box 4)
- Scrapbook material from Diaries, 1909-1942 (Box 5)
- Photo album #1 (Box 6)
- Photo album #2 (Box 7)
- Photo album #3 (Box 8)
- Photo album #4 (Box 9)
- Photo album #5 (Box 10)
- Photo album #6 (Box 11)
- Diary, 1895, Apr. 13-Sept. 13 (Box 12)
- . Athenaeum, Indianapolis, Ind. Tribute to Richard Lieber, 1933, May 19 (Folio [1])
- U. S. National Park Service. Historic sites survey. 17th century French and Spanish sites. Mimeographed. (Folio [2])
- Photographs (Folio [3])
- . Lieber Diary., 1909 (Bound [1])
- . Lieber Diary., 1910 (Bound [2])
- . Lieber Diary., 1911 (Bound [3])
- . Lieber Diary., 1912 (Bound [4])
- . Lieber Diary., 1913 (Bound [5])
- . Lieber Diary., 1914 (Bound [6])
- . Lieber Diary., 1915 (Bound [7])
- . Lieber Diary., 1916 (Bound [8])
- . Lieber Diary., 1917 (Bound [9])
- . Lieber Diary., 1918 (Bound [10])
- . Lieber Diary., 1919 (Bound [11])
- . Lieber Diary., 1920 (Bound [12])
- . Lieber Diary., 1921 (Bound [13])
- . Lieber Diary., 1922 (Bound [14])
- . Lieber Diary., 1923 (Bound [15])
- . Lieber Diary., 1924 (Bound [16])
- . Lieber Diary., 1925 (Bound [17])
- . Lieber Diary., 1926 (Bound [18])
- . Lieber Diary., 1927 (Bound [19])
- . Lieber Diary., 1928 (Bound [20])
- . Lieber Diary., 1929 (Bound [21])
- . Lieber Diary., 1930 (Bound [22])
- . Lieber Diary., 1931 (Bound [23])
- . Lieber Diary., 1932 (Bound [24])
- . Lieber Diary., 1933 (Bound [25])
- . Lieber Diary., 1934 (Bound [26])
- . Lieber Diary., 1935 (Bound [27])
- . Lieber Diary., 1936 (Bound [28])
- . Lieber Diary., 1937 (Bound [29])
- . Lieber Diary., 1938 (Bound [30])
- . Lieber Diary., 1939 (Bound [31])
- . Lieber Diary., 1940 (Bound [32])
- . Lieber Diary., 1941 (Bound [33])
- . Lieber Diary., 1942 (Bound [34])
- . Lieber Diary., 1943 (Bound [35])
- . Lieber Diary., 1944 (Bound [36])
- . Banquet at Willard Hotel Washington, D. C., 1910, Dec. 7 (Ovflat 25)
- . Family posed in front of house., 1905, Oct. 22 (Ovflat 25)
- . The "Bears" Picnic Turner Park., 1910, June 19 (Ovflat 25)
- Photographs (Ovflat 14)
- . Resolution on death of Richard Lieber, 1944, May 9 (Ovflat 14)
- n.d. Blueprint of details of fire-place in Beta Theta Pi fraternity house (Ovflat 14)
- . Receipt for use of property later known as Turkey Run State Park, Sept. 28, 1881 (Ovflat 25)
- . Military commission as Colonel and military secretary, May 11, 1917 (Ovflat 25)
- . Certificate of recognition from Chicago Regional Planning Association, 1937 (Ovflat 25)
- . Photocopy of honorary doctorate from Wabash College, June 7, 1942 (Ovflat 25)